- Hell .
- What are you stopping for ?
- I 'm stopping for a rest .
- Really Philip you can 't stop here .
For pity sake either go on or go back .
You can 't expect me to spend the night
like a half-drowned rat on a mountainside .
- It 's better to stop than drive the car
gently over a cliff , isn 't it ?
- Well it won 't help things losing your temper .
- I 've never been in a better temper in my life .
I love driving 100 miles through the dark
practically without headlights .
I love the trickle of ice cold water pouring down my neck .
This is one of the happiest moments of my life .
- Would you like me to drive for a bit ?
- Yes , I was expecting that .
- Oh , I shall be glad when we get Shrewsbury .
- If we get to Shrewsbury .
- Do you happen to have any idea where we are ?
- I haven 't the least idea in the world .
- That 's very comforting .
- You all right Penderel ?
- Fine .
Where are we ?
- We don 't know .
We 've lost our way .
We 're somewhere in the Welsh mountains , it 's half past nine
and I 'm very tired .
- Don 't mention it .
- 10 to one we don 't see Shrewsbury tonight .
- Oh well , never mind .
♫ Oh Mr. Waverton , what shall I do
♫ I wanted to go to Shrewsbury but they took me on to Crew
As a matter of fact taking one thing with another
I 'm not particularly sure that I want to go to Shrewsbury .
As far as that goes , I don 't particularly
want to go anywhere .
Something might happen here ,
but nothing ever happens in Shrewsbury .
- Something certainly might happen here .
- Well I 'll tell you something that might happen .
I don 't want to frighten Mrs. Waverton .
- Go on Mr. Penderel , I 'm not easily frightened .
- Aren 't you ?
I am .
Well , I was just going to say ,
we 'll have to be a bit careful .
- Don 't stop !
- How can I help stopping ?
Do you think we 're in a motorboat ?
♫ Stuck for the night
- Mr. Penderel please .
- Sorry .
- Do you think we 'll do it ?
- I really don 't know .
- Bon voyage .
- Well now for heaven sakes stop .
Let 's look at a map or something .
- My own view is we 're not on a map .
- Oh you look , Philip , I can 't see anything .
It 's all a stupid puddle .
- Seems to represent this country very well .
Everything here is under water .
- Oh well just drive on .
We 'll arrive somewhere , sometime .
- Yes , I suppose that 's all we can do .
♫ Singing in the bathtub
♫ Sitting all alone
♫ Tearing out a tonsil
♫ Just like a baritone
♫ Never take a shower
- Oh look , Phil , lights , lights .
Pull in there .
- Probably wisest to push on .
- Well , I 'm for staying here .
- There you are .
The whole hilltop has probably fallen off .
- Is there anybody there said the traveler ?
- Knock again , louder .
- I should have thought that was loud enough
to wake the dead .
That 's an idea .
- What is ?
- Wouldn 't it be dramatic ?
Supposing the people inside were dead ,
all stretched out with the lights
quietly burning about them .
- I 'm sure it would be very amusing .
- I 'm sure I could do with a drink .
These people have to be selfish ,
to be soaked inside not out .
- Listen .
- What is it ?
- Thought I heard something .
- Good evening .
We 've come to ask for shelter .
We 've lost our way .
We 're absolutely cut off .
Don 't you understand ?
We can 't go forward and we can 't go back .
The road 's blocked on both sides , landslide .
Even Welsh ought not sound like that .
- My name is Femm , Horace Femm .
- How do you do ?
I 'm very sorry to break in on you like this .
My name is Waverton .
May I introduce my wife ?
- How do you do ?
- Penderel .
- Charmed , I 'm sure .
- How do you do ?
- Won 't you sit down ?
- Thank you .
- My sister was on the point of arranging these flowers .
- I don 't know if your man explained the situation to you .
- He did his best , but I 'm afraid I couldn 't understand him .
You see Morgan is dumb .
- Oh I see , of course , I didn 't realize .
We saw your lights and wondered if you 'd be kind enough
to give us shelter for the night .
You see it 's quite impossible to go on .
- I see .
How awkward , how very awkward .
- What is it ?
What do they want ?
- Allow me to introduce my sister , Miss Rebecca Femm .
- How do you do ?
- What are they doing here ?
What do they want ?
- How do you do ?
- What did they say ?
What do they want ?
What are they doing here ?
What 's all the fuss about ?
What ?
- You must excuse my sister , she 's a little deaf .
In fact , sometimes quite deaf .
They want to know if they can stay here for the night .
Shelter , they 've been caught in the storm .
- Of course they can 't stay .
We can 't have them here .
- But , we only just managed
to get here as it was . - But , Miss Femm , surely - -
- It 's pouring down in torrents .
- Go on .
- You see there 's a landslide .
Half the mountain seems to be crumbling .
It only just missed us .
The road 's blocked behind us and I 'm pretty sure
it 's blocked in front as well .
We hate to intrude , but what else can we do ?
- You see there isn 't anywhere else we can go .
Even the road below is underwater and for that matter ,
this place itself may be underwater pretty soon
or even buried .
- What 's the matter ?
- Did you hear what he said ?
There 's a landslide and floods .
The lake has burst its banks .
We 're trapped , we 're trapped .
We 've got to go , you hear , we 've got to go .
- You 're afraid Horace , you 're afraid , aren 't you ?
You don 't believe in God and yet you 're afraid to die .
You 've seen his anger in the sky and you 've heard him
in the night and you 're afraid , afraid , afraid .
Where 's your mocking now ?
You might well be afraid .
Your time will come .
But , it hasn 't come yet .
This house is safe .
I know it better than you .
Morgan !
You remember the great storm years ago when we were cut off ,
there was a landslide , and floods ,
and the roads were washed away ?
Morgan remembers .
He means this house is safe because it 's built on rock .
- You will have to stay here .
The misfortune is yours not ours .
- No beds , they can 't have beds .
- As my sister hints , there are , I 'm afraid , no beds .
- That 's quite all right .
If we can just sit around the fire , that 'll be fine .
- By all means .
I 'm not very sure that I want to go to bed myself tonight .
Morgan , attend to the fire .
- Is there any place I can put the car out of the rain ?
- There are some stables round the corner to the right .
Morgan will show you .
- Thanks very much .
- I 'll come along , get the bags .
- Right .
- No bags .
You can 't have bags .
- What a storm .
- We 're well out of it .
- I hope you 're right though this house
gives me the creeps not to mention its inmates .
- Well it 's better than driving along roads
that aren 't there .
At least there 's a roof and a fire here .
- Now , Mr. Penderel do you think that you could join me
in a drink ?
- Mr. Femm , I honestly believe I could join you in a drink .
- It 's only gin , you know , only gin .
I like gin .
Mrs. Waverton .
- Thanks very much .
- Mr. Penderel I will give you a toast
that you will not appreciate being young .
I give you illusion .
- Illusion ?
Ha , I am precisely the right age for that toast , Mr. Femm .
- Oh , I presume you are one of the gentlemen
slightly , shall we say , battered by the war .
- Correct Mr. Femm .
War generation slightly soiled , a study in the bittersweet ,
the man with a twisted smile .
And , this Mr. Femm is exceedingly good gin .
- Oh dreadful night , it seems to be getting worse .
- Yes , it is pretty bad , but evidently
there 's no danger here .
Your sister was quite definite about that .
- But , supposing we 're cut off , shut up in here ?
- Well , it would be rather a nuisance for you
having us billeted on you like this .
- But , it 's awful .
How can you be so calm ?
You don 't seem to understand .
We may be cut off , shut up in this house .
I 'm afraid I 'm rather nervous .
I am rather a nervous man .
But , the fact is , Morgan is an uncivilized brute .
Sometimes he drinks heavily .
A night like this would set him going and once he 's drunk ,
he 's rather dangerous .
I don 't wish to alarm you , Mrs. Waverton ,
but I don 't quite know what we should do .
- Well , I know what I 'm going to do .
That is if Miss Femm will let me .
- What ?
- I 'm dreadfully wet and I would be so glad
if I could go and change my clothes .
- What ?
- I wondered if I might change my things .
- You look wet .
You better go and change your things .
- Oh thank you , a good idea .
Is there a bedroom or something ?
It 's a dreadful night .
- What ?
- I say , it 's a dreadful night .
- Yes , it 's a very old house , very old .
- Very kind of you to let us stay .
- What ?
- I say , you are very kind .
- Yes , it is a dreadful night .
I 'm a little deaf .
- I understand .
- Yes , no bags .
I 'll have none of this electric light , I won 't have it .
- Thanks very much .
I can manage quite well now .
- My sister Rachel had this room once .
She died when she was 21 .
She was a wicked one .
Handsome and wild as a hawk .
All the young men used to follow her about ,
with her red lips and her big eyes and her white neck .
But , that didn 't save her .
She fell off her horse , hunting , hurt her spine .
On this bed she lay month after month .
Many the time I sat here listening to her screaming .
- How dreadful .
- She used to cry out to me to kill her .
But I 'd tell her to turn to the Lord .
But , she didn 't .
She was godless to the last .
- Well , I 'd better change my wet things .
- They were all godless here .
They used to bring their women here .
Brazen , lolling creatures in silks and satins .
They filled the house with laughter and sin ,
laughter and sin .
If I ever went down among them , my own father and brothers ,
they would tell me to go away and pray .
They wouldn 't tell Rachel to go away and pray .
And , I prayed and left them
with their lustful red and white women .
My father 's still alive .
He 's upstairs .
He 's very old .
- Oh is he ?
- He 's 102 .
- That 's very old , isn 't it ?
- He 's a wicked , blasphemous old man .
You 're wicked too , young and handsome , silly , and wicked .
You think of nothing but your long , straight legs
and your white body and how to please your man .
You revel in the joys of fleshly love , don 't you ?
That 's fine stuff , but it 'll rot .
That 's finer stuff still , but it 'll rot too in time .
- Don 't .
How dare you ?
- Brazen , lolling creatures in silks and satins .
Laughter and sin , laughter and sin .
Lustful red and white women .
- Good for you , Mrs. Waverton ,
you make it look like a party .
- Thank you .
You must have thought I was a long time .
- Matter of fact , I thought you were quicker than usual .
- Oh , I just thought I 'd been rather long .
- Supper .
- Philip .
- Horace , what are you doing ?
We aren 't all heathens .
- Oh , I had forgotten my sister 's strange tribal habits .
The beef will seem less tough when she has invoked
a blessing upon it .
- Horace Femm , I can 't hear , I can see , you 're blaspheming .
- Oh the contrary , my dear Rebecca .
I was merely telling your wondering guests
that you were about to thank your gods for their bounty .
- That 'll do .
I know your mocking , lying tongue .
- To thank them for the health and prosperity
and happiness granted to this family .
For its years of peace and plenty ,
to thank them for having created Rebecca Femm
and Roderick Femm and Saul - -
- Stop !
- Bless oh Lord , this is the house ,
may they prove a wholesome ,
healing remedy for mankind , amen .
- Have a potato .
- Thank you .
- Well , this is a storm and a half .
- Yes , isn 't it ?
- Have a potato .
- Thank you , I should love a potato .
Vinegar , Miss Femm ?
- It 's simply coming down in bucket fulls outside .
- Thank you Mrs. Waverton , that 's the phrase
I 've been searching for all evening .
- No , no pickled onions , thank you .
- Oh those lights , they gave me quite a start .
I suppose it 's the storm .
- On the contrary .
We make our own electric lights here
and we are not very good at it .
Pray , don 't be alarmed if they go out altogether .
- There 's someone outside .
- They can 't come in .
- But , surely they must come in .
It 's probably dangerous out there now .
- They 're probably half-drowned .
You know really we oughtn 't to keep them waiting .
- No , I 'm afraid we shall have to let them in .
Morgan , open the door .
- Come on then , Morgan , let them in .
- Woo , what a night .
- I thought you were never going to open that door .
By .
There must have been a reservoir burst or something .
Anyhow , before we knew where we were ,
something had fallen down and smashed the car in .
It 's a wonder it didn 't smash us .
Incidentally , this house will probably
be washed away any minute .
- Aye .
Oh , look at that .
Oh , that 's a grand fire .
I 'm sorry to barge in on you like this ,
but needs must when the devil drives .
Well , who 's the owner here ?
- My sister is the owner , Miss Femm .
- How do you do , Miss Femm ?
My name is Porterhouse , Sir William Porterhouse .
And , this lady is Miss Gladys Duquesne ,
a friend of mine .
- Glad to know you .
Nice weather for ducks .
- Allow me to introduce you .
This is Mrs. Waverton .
- How do you do ?
- And , Mr. Penderel .
- How do you do , Sir William .
- And , Mr. Waverton .
- How do you do ?
- Sir William Porterhouse .
I 've never seen such a night in all my born natural .
I 'll tell you , it 's coming down in bucket fulls .
Pretty well soaked we were , I don 't mind telling you .
I shouldn 't be surprised if we caught our deaths .
- Here , you better not put those wet shoes on again
or as Sir William points out ,
you 'll probably catch your death .
Here you are .
These may not be exactly your size ,
but at least they 're dry .
- Thanks , they 'll do fine .
Wee , ha ha .
♫ Da di di di bum bum
♫ Bum bum bum bum bum bum
- Are you fond of opera , Mr. ?
- Come and have something to eat .
- Oh , now you 're talking .
- Morgan , bring up some chairs .
- Oh oh , roast beef , ha .
There 's nothing like roast beef when a man 's hungry .
♫ Oh the roast beef of old England
How does that go ?
Do you remember that Mr. Waverton
or was that before your time ?
- Penderel 's our song expert .
- Oh , so you 're musical , are ya ?
Well , I 've got a bit of an ear myself .
- Have a potato .
Morgan , bring a glass of water for Sir William .
- Oh thanks very much .
Take ourselves for instance .
Here we are six people sitting around
and we 've been talking now for nearly two hours .
What do we know about each other ?
Not a thing .
- How reassuring .
- I agree with Sir William , at best we only make guesses .
- If you were a woman , you wouldn 't talk about only guesses .
- Ah , the famous old feminine intuition .
Does it ever tell you which horse is going to win the Derby ?
- No , but it tells me quite a lot about you .
- I wonder , Mrs. Waverton , whether it happens to tell you
that I am wanted by the police ?
- Why no , Mr. Femm , it tells me nothing so romantic .
- After all , can you conceive of anybody
living in a house like this if they didn 't have to ?
- Well , there 's no accounting for tastes , you know .
- No .
- Miss Duquesne .
- Yes .
- What does your intuition tell you about me ?
- Quite a lot .
- Hmm , that frightens me a good deal .
- What does it tell you ?
- It tells me ...
Well , it 's not very interesting anyway .
- Oh yes it is .
Let 's have it .
- Well , it sounds silly , but
I think he doesn 't quite fit into these times ,
you know factories and cheap advertising
and money grubbing and well , what I mean is ,
Bill here 's all right with these things .
But , they make Mr. Penderel a kind of fish out of water .
- You should be flattered , Mr. Penderel .
- No , I 'm not flattered .
You see I 've not much sympathy with fish out of water ,
although I happen to be one myself .
My trouble is , I don 't think enough things are worthwhile .
Now , Sir William here would put tremendous energy
into anything to make even a few pounds .
Now , I don 't think it 's worth it .
- No doubts you think I 'm fat-headed my young friend ,
but maybe I can see through things a bit further
than you suppose .
That was a very fine speech of yours ,
but I know , as well as everybody else here ,
that you 're really only getting at me .
- Well , honestly I wasn 't doing anything of the kind .
I envy you , I admire you .
- Oh yes , you envy me all right ,
but you don 't admire me .
Huh , well , I don 't admire myself so much .
I know that money-making isn 't everything ,
but let me tell you something .
I 'm a young man , see .
Married to a Manchester girl , pretty as paint .
The only thing in the world I care about .
Well , she dies .
It 's this way , my directors give a party .
They ask us .
Red letter day for us , I can tell ya .
I buy my first dress suit and Lucy has a new frock .
A cotton frock .
It seems that Lucy didn 't go too well at that party
especially with the women .
They snubbed her .
Nothing definite , you know , just didn 't think
the cotton frock was good enough .
Well Lucy worries about it .
Gets it into her head that she 's gonna hold me back .
Well , you may not believe it , but I know
that 's what killed her .
That 's what started me making money .
I swore I 'd smash those fellows and their wives
that wouldn 't give my Lucy a kind word .
Ha , and I have smashed ' em .
I 'd raced most of ' em .
Once you 've started making money , it 's hard to stop ,
especially if you 're like me , there isn 't much else
you 're good at .
But , what Gladys here has to be superior about
I don 't know , Miss Duquesne .
Why don 't you tell ' em your real name ?
- My real name is Perkins .
- And , a very nice name , too .
- I may not be this and I may not be that ,
but you don 't catch me pretending to be
what I 'm not .
- I think I 'm finding you a little bit offensive .
- That 's all right , Mr. Penderel , I can take care of myself .
Least if I can 't by now , I never will be able to .
I wasn 't trying to put anything across you , Bill .
I don 't pretend to be what I 'm not either .
I 'm not as dumb as that .
These people here know a chorus girl when they see one .
And , incidentally not a very good
chorus girl at that .
If I were better at my job ,
I probably wouldn 't be weekending with you .
No , I take that back , I probably would .
You 're nice enough .
We get on , but ...
- Morgan 's at the bottle again .
I knew he 'd begin again tonight .
Where 'd he get it from ?
- He didn 't get it from me .
Can 't you stop him .
- He 's in the kitchen now drunk , quite drunk .
- Who 's Morgan ?
Is he the fellow that waited on us at table ?
- Yes , Morgan is the , the butler .
- Looks to me as if he could do
with a shave .
- Oh hello .
- Hello .
- Well , have you come over to help me gaze up upon
the wrath of God ?
- No , I came to say thank you for trying
to take my part just now .
- Charmed , I 'm sure , Miss Duquesne .
- Perkins to you .
- Nice Perkins .
- I say I 'd mortgage the old homestead for a drink .
- Hhmm , so would I.
And , we 'll have one .
I 've got some whiskey in the car .
I 'd forgotten all about it .
You stay here and I 'll go and get it .
- No , I 'll come with you .
Woo , wee .
- You better stay here undercover .
The car 's in the stables and you 'll get soaked .
- All right , don 't be long .
Mr. Penderel .
- Hello , what are you doing here ?
I was just coming .
- I thought I 'd come fetch you .
- Hey , hey , what 's the matter ?
What 's happened ?
- Nothing , nothing really .
Got a bit scared , that 's all .
Somebody slammed the door in my face .
- Probably the wind .
- No , it wasn 't .
I know wind when I see it .
It doesn 't sound much , but well you know ,
it gave me bit of a turn .
- Yes , I bet it did .
Here , what you want 's a drink of this .
- Thanks .
I feel a bit more human now .
- This certainly is a benighted household .
- You were right , it is .
- Look at those .
Come on , take ' em off .
I seem to spend most of the evening changing your shoes .
- You ought to be a nursery maid .
- Yes , except that the best nursery maids
don 't drink whiskey out of the bottle .
- Storm 's just as bad as ever , isn 't it ?
- Worse .
- That 's done it , the light 's gone out .
- I suppose they 'll stay out this time .
Now we should be miserable all the evening .
- That 's all right .
Surely there 's some candles somewhere , aren 't there ?
- Can 't do anything about the lights , Miss Femm ?
- No , nobody understands our lights except Morgan .
And as an electrician , Morgan is temporarily disqualified .
- You haven 't got a lamp by any chance , have you ?
- No , no , we haven 't got a lamp .
- What did they say ?
- Nothing , nothing important .
- Oh , nothing important
Well , as happens I heard that time .
They want a lamp .
Give them the large one .
There 's oil in it .
We used it the last time the lights went wrong .
Go on , Horace , you know the one .
- I don 't remember where it is .
Suppose you get it , Rebecca ?
- It 's too big for me .
If you don 't know where it is , I 'll tell you .
You know as well as I do .
It 's on the top landing on the little table .
Do you know where the top landing is , Horace ?
Least you might believe there is a top landing ,
although you do believe in so little .
It 's up there , Horace , up there ,
next to the roof .
- Yes , of course , I remember .
But , I think it 's a little too heavy for me .
I don 't think I could carry it down all those stairs .
- Why don 't you say what you mean , Horace ?
You mean that you 're afraid to go up there alone .
You go with him .
Here take this .
I don 't know why I bother myself .
Do you all good to sit in the dark .
- We better go up , hadn 't we ?
- Yes , I suppose we had .
- We won 't be long .
- That 's all right , Mrs. Waverton will see
that I don 't get nervy .
- You 'd better lead the way .
- This is my room .
- Oh ?
- There are one or two things that I should very much like
for you to see .
- I should like to very much but you must show me
some other time .
We 've gotta get that lamp .
- Yes .
Listen , why should we bother about the lamp ?
Let us wait here for a few minutes
and then go back and say that we couldn 't find it
or that it 's broken .
- I can 't see the point .
- Yes but why should we trouble about the lamp
if we don 't want to ?
- But , we said we 'd get it so why shouldn 't we get it .
- Yes , but why should we if we don 't want to
and I don 't want to .
- But , this is absurd ...
Did you hear that ?
- I did hear something .
- What was it ?
- It must have been Morgan .
He 's drunk , you know .
He 's probably making a disturbance
downstairs in the kitchen .
- I thought that noise came from upstairs .
Anyway , what about this lamp ?
- I wondered whether you would excuse me
from coming with you .
I 'm not very strong .
There are rather a lot of stairs .
I really should have told you before ,
but the vanity of age , you know .
You 'll find it on a little table at the end
of the landing two floors above .
- I suppose it 's not too heavy for me to carry .
- Oh not at all .
It 's quite light really .
- I see .
- Thank you , thank you very much .
- You opened it , didn 't you ?
Well now you can go and shut it .
Go on , shut it , I can 't .
- Go and shut what ?
- The rain 's pouring and the flood 's rising .
The room will be drenched if you don 't come quickly .
- She means the window in her room .
I 'm afraid I opened it .
- Go on , you opened it , you can shut it .
- That 's all right , Miss Femm , I 'll come and shut it .
- Now .
Mr. Penderel , Miss Duquesne .
It 's Morgan , he 's there at the bottom of the stairs .
- Take the candle , get back there .
Get back , go on , get back .
- Is he dead ?
- No you can see him breathing from here .
He 's only stunned .
He 'll be conscious in a minute ,
though he 'll probably fall asleep again .
He 's very drunk .
- Oh Philip , this is an awful house .
- It isn 't very nice , is it ?
Listen , Margaret , something happened upstairs just now .
- Oh Philip , not something else horrible .
- No this was nothing horrible .
It was a voice calling from behind a door ,
tiny voice , rather like a child 's .
I think I ought to go and see what it is .
You 'll have to come with me .
I 'm not gonna leave you alone again .
He 'll be all right .
Take my hand , darling .
- Oh Philip .
- What is it ?
Sit down here a minute , darling .
- Thanks .
- Well , what happened then ?
- Well , then the war ended .
- What about the girl ?
- Oh , the girl I left behind me .
- The girl you were in love with .
- Why she got married , Gladys .
- What a beast .
- No , on the contrary , a lady of rather good judgment .
But , now let 's talk about you for a bit .
- I know what you were going to say .
You were going to ask me about Bill Porterhouse .
- Clever , Miss Perkins .
- I don 't mind telling you .
I 'd rather like to .
Bill 's all right , really .
Of course , I don 't love him .
And , of course , he gives me money .
Oh not very much , just enough to keep me going .
You probably won 't believe me , but Bill doesn 't ,
he doesn 't expect anything .
Do you know what I mean by anything ?
- Yes , I know what you mean by anything .
- He likes people to think he 's ever so gay .
You see , for all his money , he 's a bit lonely .
- Yes , I spotted that when he told us the story
of the cotton dress .
I think he 's in love with that little dead wife still .
- I 'm sure he is .
I suppose that 's why he only wants me , well , for company .
He likes to sit on my bed at night and boast to me
about the things he 's done during the day .
- Well , that 's harmless enough .
- Mind you , I 'm not pretending to be any better than I am .
- You 're a nice creature , aren 't you ?
- I like you , awfully .
- And , I you .
- What are you thinking of ?
- You may not be very pleased .
- Risk it .
- I was thinking I 'd like to pretend that I was your lover
and that you were mine , Gladys , body and soul .
I 'd like to take you in my arms and hold you
and press you to me very gently , very tight .
- I 'd like it too .
- Would you , Gladys Perkins ?
Why then , let 's pretend .
- Listen .
Gladys Perkins has an idea .
I think she must have gone mad .
She , she , she wants to live with you .
Oh , I 'm just flinging myself at your head .
I 've got a crazy idea
that I might help you to be a useful person .
- Darling Perkins .
- Do you think I 'm mad ?
- Quite mad , my darling and thank God for it .
- Well , what do you say ?
- That 's what I say , Perkins darling .
But , I 've got a better idea than yours ,
an improvement on it .
- What is it ?
- Why it 's just this ...
No , I won 't tell you here .
There 's magic here .
I 'll tell you later on in the house ,
perhaps even in the cold light of morning .
- Tell me now .
- Come on , let 's go back to the house .
- No , no let 's stay here .
- You 're cold .
- No , it 's just the idea of going back to that house
that made me shiver .
I 've got a funny feeling something dreadful
might happen to us if we go back to that house .
- Perkins , Perkins , you 've my strong right arm , haven 't you ?
- All right , come on .
- No , you can 't put on those wet shoes .
I 'm going to try to carry you .
- I 'm a devil of a weight .
- Well , if you 're too heavy for me ,
I shall drop you in the mud and go on alone .
- Hello , where have you been ?
- I went out to the car to get a drink .
- And , I went with him .
- She got her feet wet .
- Oh , she got her feet wet ?
- Yes , she got her feet wet .
Well , what the devil 's been happening here ?
- I don 't know what the devil 's been happening here
or anywhere else .
I don 't know what 's been happening anywhere .
I went into the old girl 's room to close the window
and came back and found this .
- Well , where are all the others ?
- I don 't know no more than you .
Mr. Waverton went upstairs with
to fetch a lamp .
I suppose his wife joined him .
I 've been asleep .
So , you got your feet wet ?
- Yes , Bill , and that wasn 't all either .
- Yes , I didn 't suppose it was .
- Don 't quite know how you 'll take this
but well , I 've got to get it off my chest .
- Come on , let 's have it .
- I 've fallen in love , Bill .
- Oh you have , have you ?
With him ?
- Yes with him .
- Damned fool .
- Probably , but we don 't choose these things .
- Has he got any money ?
- Not a penny .
- But , you 're going off with him ?
- Yes , Bill .
Are you angry ?
- I think you 're a lunatic ,
but I 'm not angry .
- He took it pretty well , didn 't he , Perkins ?
- I told you , Bill 's all right .
- He is indeed .
- Wonder where the others can be ?
- Listen , Bill , she hasn 't told you everything .
- Hasn 't she ?
Why not ?
- Because she doesn 't know everything herself .
We 're going to be married .
- Oh , are ya ?
- At least if she 'll have me .
I 'm going to ask her tomorrow in the cold light of morning .
Will you come to the wedding ?
- I think you 're off your head .
- Do you ?
- No , I don 't .
I think it 's probably the best day 's work you 've ever done
in your life .
- Ah , Bill , Bill .
- Who told you that you could call me Bill ?
- Well , you try and stop me .
- Now look here , come and make yourself useful
and put this table on its feet .
That 's no way to treat roast beef .
- Miss Perkins , tend the roast beef .
- Tend it yourself .
- Sure you feel better ?
- Yes , I 'm all right .
- Well let 's go on .
This is the door .
- Who are you ?
- I 'm Mrs. Waverton .
This is my husband .
Are you Sir Roderick Femm ?
We came in because we thought we heard you calling .
Can we get you anything ?
Can you take it yourself or shall I give it to you ?
- I can take it myself , thank you .
What was that noise ?
Was it Morgan ?
- Yes .
- Morgan is a savage .
I must apologize .
But , we have to keep him here .
You shouldn 't have come here .
- Well , I 'm very sorry , but really we couldn 't help it .
- Oh I , I don 't mean that .
I was never inhospitable , never .
This house was always filled with guests
once upon a time .
When you came , what did they tell you ?
- Why , they told us you were an invalid .
- Was that all ?
- Yes .
- You 've seen my son Horace and his sister Rebecca .
- And , Morgan .
I would like to tell you all about it ,
but there may not be time .
You see , when you 're as old as I am ,
at any minute , you may just die .
- Oh please don 't talk if it tires you .
- This is an unlucky house .
Two of my children died when they were 20 .
And , then other things happened .
Madness came .
We are all touched with it a little you see ,
except me , at least
I don 't think I am .
- Would you like to go to sleep now ?
No , not just yet .
You see , it may be ...
- It may be what ?
- Dangerous .
- You mean Morgan ?
- No , not Morgan .
I mean from my eldest son , Saul .
- Saul ?
- They didn 't tell you about Saul .
- No , they didn 't .
- Saul is the worst , you know .
We have to watch him because you see ,
he wants , he just wants
to destroy , to kill .
Poor Saul .
- Where is he ?
- I know where he is .
He 's upstairs behind that bolted door , isn 't he ?
- Yes , locked in .
Saul is why we have to keep Morgan .
- But , if he did get out ?
- Saul quite certainly would set fire to the house .
He tried to once before .
He wanted he said to make this house a burnt offering .
- But , isn 't he safely locked in ?
- Yes , but you see , if Morgan is bad ,
I , I think he might
open the door .
- Philip , what if he 's come to .
- Wait here , I 'll go down and look at him .
- He 's gone upstairs .
I heard him .
He 's gone to let Saul out .
Wait for him downstairs and kill him .
- What are we to do ?
Can 't we stay in here ?
- No supposing he set fire to the place .
Come on .
- But , what about Sir Roderick ?
- We must lock the door .
Sir Roderick , I 'm going to lock you in .
- He 's asleep .
- What is it ?
- Listen , there 's a madman upstairs .
Morgan 's let him out and he 's dangerous .
We 've got to do something .
- Good gosh where are they ?
- Upstairs but they may come down any minute .
- That 's all right , my dear .
- I knew I felt something dreadful was going to happen .
- Hadn 't we better get out of the way ?
- No , we can 't do that .
He might set fire to the place .
He 's tried it once before .
- Well let him , let the rotten old place burn .
I wish it would .
- That 's all right , what about the Femms ?
- What is it ?
- Your brother 's out of his room .
- What , Saul ?
- Look !
- Here get back .
- Take him back , Morgan , you hear me , take him back .
- Take him in the kitchen .
Take him this way .
- Oh , that hurts .
- Trap him in the kitchen .
The sins of the fathers , the sins of the fathers .
Come on you , come into my room .
- No , I 'm going to stay here .
- Then stay there .
- There 's going to be trouble .
- Oh Penderel .
- Come on , come in here .
- No , I don 't want to be shut out .
I 'd rather stay .
- Gladys for heaven sake come in here .
Margaret .
- Oh , no , all right .
- Wait a minute .
Here , light this .
- Oh , I love him so .
I just love him .
- Please , please don 't touch me .
- Well , what is it ?
- Listen , don 't put me back , don 't let them put me back .
I 'm not mad .
I swear before heaven I 'm not mad .
It 's just that they 've locked me up here .
They 're all wicked .
- Well why should they lock you up ?
- They 're frightened of me .
I know something about them .
Years ago , they killed their sister Rachel .
But , I wouldn 't tell , I promised I 'd never tell .
- And , they 've kept you here all that time for that ?
- And , Morgan , I tell you he 's the devil .
Morgan beats me .
Don 't leave me , stay with me .
- Well that 's all right .
You sit here and wait .
I 'll be back .
The door 's locked .
Miss Femm must 've locked it .
- It 's locked is it ?
- Yes , it is .
- I 'm glad .
Then you can 't leave me .
- Listen , we 've got to help the others with Morgan .
Isn 't there some way of getting through ?
- No , no way .
- Well , there must be a back entrance into the house .
- Stop .
I want to tell you a story .
Who 's in there ?
- Nobody .
- Friends of yours ?
- I tell you , nobody .
- Shall we invite them out ?
- You were going to tell me something .
- Yes , so I was .
- Won 't you , won 't you tell me that story ?
- Yes , shall we sit down ?
- Yes , let 's .
- Who 's in that cupboard ?
- Nobody .
Tell me what you were going to say to me .
- Are you interested in flames ?
- Why , why yes , yes I am rather .
- I 've made a study of flame .
- Have you ?
Well , that must be very interesting to you .
- I know things about flames that nobody else
in the world knows .
- Well , won 't you tell me ?
I 'd like very much to know .
- Why should I tell you ?
You wouldn 't tell me who is in that cupboard .
- Oh but I did tell you .
Besides you know it isn 't fair to make me curious
and then just not say anything .
- You 'd like me to tell you all about fire , would you ?
- Yes , I wish you would .
- Well then , first of all , I 've learned
that flames are really knives .
They 're cold , my friend .
Sharp and cold as snow .
They burn like ice .
- Oh that certainly is very , very interesting .
So , they 're really like knives , are they ?
Well , do go on .
Tell me what else , you 've found out .
- Oh a lot of things .
My friend , sit down .
So , you thought you could cheat me , did you ?
You thought you could leave me sitting here
and I wouldn 't notice .
But , you see I am a clever man also .
That is why we understand one another .
That is why you understood so quickly
that I wanted to kill you .
We understand each other so well ,
don 't we , my friend ?
- Yes , yes indeed we do .
From the start somehow I liked you
and I thought you liked me .
- Like you ?
My friend , I love you .
Did you know my name is Saul ?
Saul , my friend .
And , Saul loved David .
- Yes , indeed he did .
- But , Saul was afraid of David because the Lord
was with him and was departed from Saul .
And , it came to pass on the morrow
that the evil spirit came upon Saul and he prophesied
in the midst of the house .
And , David played upon the harp with his hand
and there was a javelin in Saul 's hand
and Saul cast the javelin .
And , he said , " I will smite David even to the wall with it . "
And , David avoided out of his presence
twice , twice , my friend .
But , the third time , the third time ,
you must be careful .
- Listen , I 'm your friend .
I 'm in your side .
It 's silly to lose me .
If you lose me , look there 's Morgan ,
he 's come for you , Morgan .
- Stop .
Don 't move .
Oh !
- Philip , Philip .
Philip .
- Oh , let go , can 't you see , there 's Penderel ?
Let me go to him .
Go on , let me go by .
Go on , let me pass .
Oh you swine .
But , I 'm not afraid of you .
I 'm going to him , do you hear ?
- Oh , how could you ?
Listen , you 've get to let me alone , do you hear ?
I 've got to go to Penderel , he 's hurt .
Oh , how can I make you understand ?
He 's hurt .
I 've got to look after him and the other man too , Saul .
They 're both hurt .
- Are you all right , Margaret ?
- Yes , I 'm all right , darling .
- Gladys , it 's all right .
Come on , now .
Here , you feeling better ?
- Yes , I 'm not so bad .
- What happened to you ?
- That was Morgan , he hit her .
- Come on .
- I 'm all right now .
Where 's Penderel ?
I 've got to look after him .
- You 'd better not go over there .
Come with me .
- Oh .
- He 's alive !
- What ?
- He 's alive , I tell you , he 's alive .
Oh , oh .
- Good morning .
- Good morning , Mr. Waverton .
- The floods have subsided considerably .
- Thank heaven for that .
- I think it will be possible for you
to send for an ambulance now .
- You mean we can go ?
- Yes , I 'm sure we can go now .
Come along , darling .
- You 're going to stay here with Gladys , aren 't you ?
- I am .
Don 't be long .
- We won 't .
We 'll be as quick as we can .
- Good bye .
So happy to have met you .
- Ah cha !
- So , I 'm really dead and gone to heaven .
- No , it 's morning and we 've only just their tail behind .
- Morning ?
- Yes , cold light of day .
Wasn 't there something you were going to tell me
in the cold light of day ?
- Come to think of it , there was .
- Perkins , will you marry me ?